Why did every great power try to conquer
China? And how did they succeed? After
winning a war in 1895, Japan seized the
strategic prize of Port Arthur, but
Russia, France, and Germany, fearing a
powerful Japan, forced them to give it
back. Russia's obsession was that same
port. In 1898, they forced China to
lease it to them. But their dream was
shattered when a vengeful Japan crushed
them in the Russo-Japanese War of 1905
and took it back. Britain, the dominant
power, wanted to control China's entire
economy through the rich Yangty River
Valley. But their ambition was
constantly blocked by competing powers.
Germany had been preoccupied with Europe
and arrived late. So in 1897, they used
the murder of two missionaries as a
brutal excuse to seize the port of Ching
Dao. Other powers really hated this
aggressive move. The United States,
fearing it would be shut out, demanded
an open door policy in 1899 that would
prevent anyone from building an empire
that America couldn't exploit.